Guide to the Pierce-Dahlgren-Vinton Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Pierce-Dahlgren-Vinton family papers
1792-1936
MS 398
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.25
(16 boxes)
The principal figure in these papers is Sarah Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren, whose daughter, Ulrica Dahlgren married Josiah Pierce (1861-1902). More than half the papers consists of family correspondence chiefly for the years 1824-1873. Also in included are sketchbooks, memoirs, genealogical materials, account books, legal records and autographs of Civil War generals and admirals. The correspondence of Josiah Pierce (1827-1913) who was secretary of the U.S. legation in St. Petersburg includes material documenting his service in Russia. Also in the papers is the diary (in Russian) of Ivan Timofieff for the year 1858, with an English translation. The papers of Samuel Finley Vinton, who was congressman from Ohio (1823-1837; 1843-1851) include courtship letters to his fiancée.
Pierce family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited by Joan Dahlgren Pierce, 1953-1954.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged by name of family member.
Biographical / Historical
Sarah Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren: author; married Daniel C. Goddard, 1846, married Rear Admiral John Adolphus Dahlgren, 1865; began to write professionally in 1859, author of many books and articles. Josiah Pierce (1861-1902): civil engineer; from 1883-1884 served as engineer on the Northern Trans-continental Survey; from 1885-1888 served in the U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey; in the 1890s was connected with various railroad companies and utility companies; professor of engineering at the Columbian University and Catholic University of America.
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Pierce-Dahlgren-Vinton family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Scope and Contents
The principal figure in these papers is Sarah Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren, whose daughter, Ulrica Dahlgren married Josiah Pierce (1861-1902). More than half the papers consists of family correspondence chiefly for the years 1824-1873. Also in included are sketchbooks, memoirs, genealogical materials, account books, legal records and autographs of Civil War generals and admirals. The correspondence of Josiah Pierce (1827-1913) who was secretary of the U.S. legation in St. Petersburg includes material documenting his service in Russia. Also in the papers is the diary (in Russian) of Ivan Timofieff for the year 1858, with an English translation. The papers of Samuel Finley Vinton, who was congressman from Ohio (1823-1837; 1843-1851) include courtship letters to his fiancée.
Armed Forces; Courtship; Engineering; Families; Women; Europe; Ohio -- Description and travel; Saint Petersburg (Russia) -- Description and travel; Soviet Union; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Washington (D.C.) -- Social life and customs; Account books; Autobiographies (documents); Autographs (manuscripts); Diaries; Authors; Civil engineers; Diplomats; Engineers; Bureau, John Peter Romaine, 1770-1854; Dahlgren, John Adolphus Bernard, 1809-1870; Dahlgren, Madeleine Vinton, 1825-1898; Dahlgren, Ulric, 1842-1864; Goddard, Daniel Convers, 1822-1852; Pierce, Eliza West, 1859-1877; Pierce, Eliza, 1838-1879; Pierce, Evelina Lewis, 1795-1870; Pierce, Franklin, 1804-1869; Pierce, George Washington, 1836-1910; Pierce, Josiah, 1792-1866; Pierce, Josiah, 1827-1913; Pierce, Josiah, 1861-1902; Pierce, Lewis, b. 1832; Pierce, Martha Derby Lander, 1834-1873; Vinton family; Vinton, Romaine Madeleine Bureau, 1802-1831; Vinton, Samuel Finley, 1792-1862; Dahlgren family; Pierce family
- Inventory
  - Correspondence (with some legal papers, autographs, printed matter, etc,; also some letters are filed under recipient rather than author), Circa (1824-1869)-1936
    - A -Dahlgren, P. (Box 1)
    - Dahlgren, S. - Goddard, D.C. (Box 2)
    - Goddard, D.C. (cont'd) - Sm (Box 3)
    - St -Vinton, S. F. (Box 4)
    - Vinton, S. F. (cont'd) -Y, unidentified (Box 5)
  - Dahlgren, John Adolphus Bernard: journals, notebooks, letters patent, Circa 1829-1866 (Box 6)
  - Dahlgren, Sarah Madeleine (Vinton) Goddard
    - Commonplace book, 1839-1841 (Box 6)
    - Memoir of Daniel C. Goddard: MS notebook, 1853 (Box 6)
    - Vinton estate inventories, 1889-1898 (Box 6)
    - "Reminiscence": typescript, undated (Box 6)
  - Dahlgren, Ulric
    - Sketchbook, 1850 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence and MSS for memoir of him, Circa 1862-1865, 1886 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence and MSS for memoir of him, Circa 1862-1865, 1886 (Box 7)
  - Dahlgren, William Theodore (alia William de Rohan), 1855-1891 (Box 7)
    - Letters received, 1855-1891 (Box 7)
    - Letters from; passports; subject files (France, Italy, Mexico and Texas, Sweden, Turkey); miscellaneous, Circa 1836-1888 (Box 8)
  - Goddard, Vinton
    - Order and letterbooks, 1873-1876 (Box 8)
    - Notebooks of writings, drawings, addresses, 1868, undated (Box 8)
  - Lander, Frederick West: correspondence, orders, clippings, Circa 1817, 1853-1862 (Box 9)
  - Pierce, Eliza: book inscribed to her, 1874 (Box 9)
  - Pierce, Josiah (1756-1830): "Road to Happiness by a Parent": MS, with copy by Josiah Pierce (1827 - 1913), 1824, 1846 (Box 9)
  - Pierce, Josiah (1827-1913), Circa 1832-1873 (Box 9)
    - Letters to, from, and about
      - A-M (Box 9)
      - N-Pierce, J. (Box 10)
      - Pierce, J (cont'd)-Pierce, M. (Box 11)
      - Pierce, M. (cont'd)-W (Box 12)
    - Correspondence and clippings re: Emperor Alexander II of Russia, 1860-1867 (Box 12)
    - Memorandum book, commonplace book, speech, 1845-[1850?] (Box 13)
    - Diary kept by Ivan [Timofieff?], in Russian with English translation, 1858 (Box 13)
    - Account books, financial papers, Circa 1843-1864 (Box 13)
    - Certificates, legal papers, printed memorabilia, Circa 1842-1868 (Box 13)
    - Passports, Circa 1849-1868 (Box 13)
    - Memoranda, miscellaneous papers, Circa 1844-1858 (Box 13)
  - Pierce, Josiah (1861-1902)
    - Letter to Cardinal Gibbons, 1891 (Box 14)
    - Drawings, printed memorabilia, 1891, 1900, undated (Box 14)
  - Pierce, ___: miscellaneous and unidentified, Circa 1838-1855 (Box 14)
  - Vinton, Samuel Finley
    - Deeds, Circa 1792-1845 (Box 14)
    - Notebook, 1822, undated (Box 14)
    - [Vinton and others]: miscellaneous apers, Circa 1816-1869 (Box 14)
  - Unidentified and unsorted
    - Genealogical and biographical writings, notes, tables, Circa (1814-1872)-1923 (Box 14)
    - Bills, receipts, deeds, Circa 1816-1867 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, Circa 1804-1865 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence and notes, 1859-1912 (Box 14)
    - Photostats of Lincoln's diary, 1861 (Box 14)
    - Autographs of Civil War generals and admirals, Circa 1818-1898 (Box 14)
  - Unidentified and unsorted (cont'd)
    - "Miss West": music book, undated (Box 14)
    - Recipe book, 1929 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous writings, 1825-1836, undated (Box 14)
    - Memorabilia, undated (Box 15)
    - Calling cards, undated (Box 15)
    - Maps, undated (Box 15)
    - Printed matter: clippings, pamphlets, miscellaneous, Circa 1827-1928 (Box 15)
    - Printed matter: clippings, pamphlets, miscellaneous, Circa 1827-1928 (Box 16)
    - Photographs, Circa 1862-1896, undated (Box 16)
    - Empty envelopes and binders, undated (Box 16)